[Voices of children playing and laughing]
[B.Z. Goldberg] Growing up here
in Jerusalem,
I think I had a pretty normal childhood.
But normal in the Middle East
is always intertwined with war.
Fighting breaks out,
bombs blow up, people are killed.
When the peace talks began,
I came back to Jerusalem.
My name is B.Z. What's your name?
- Mecideh
I knew the children here
had something to say
and no one was asking them
what they thought of the conflict
or the peace process.
[foreign dialogue]
[speaking in foreign language]
This film is about seven Palestinian
and Israeli children,
we met in and around Jerusalem.
They live no more than 20 minutes
from each other,
but they are each growing up
in very separate worlds.
[camera flash]
[wind blowing]
- My name is Yarko.
Yarko Solan.
- My name is Daniel.
- Bye!
- Daniel, why are you wearing
the same clothes as me?
- You're wearing the same clothes as me!
- I got dressed first.
- Right! You get up like an old cow.
There were lots of terrorist attacks
on the number 18 bus.
People avoid the number 18, which is
dumb 'cause if I take the number 22
which is supposed to be a safe line,
I could still blow up.
When I get on I'm anxious,
so I look for suspicious people.
If I see a really scary person,
I watch him.
I try to get off before he does.
I keep waiting for the explosion
When we're downtown -
most of the explosion are downtown.
So I can't wait to get past the downtown area, I count the seconds-
It could happen anywhere!
It's rare. It only happens once a year.
It could happen once a year to YOU.
So?
So!? And then you'll die.
So?! You don't care if you die?
I do care. So I protect myself.
How do you protect yourself?
I say: OMMMMMMMM.
[water boiling]
[speaking in Palestinian]
My name is
Mahmoud Mazen Mahmoud Izhiman.
They named me that becaues I'm
Mahmoud, My dad is Mazen --
My grandfather was also Mahmoud
and my family is Izhiman!
- Coffee? Sssh, don't tell anyone.
Sometimes I drink coffee
at my grandmother's house.
[coffee grinding]
If my mother knew I drank coffee,
she'd shoot me.
She's afraid it will make me
grow a mustache!
The Jews say this is their land.
How could it be their land?
If it is their land, why does Koran
say that the Prophet, Mohammed--
flew from theMecca to the
Al Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem.
So, Jerusalem belongs to us!
To the Arabs!
- Flomo is the son of a well-respected Rabii
from the United States.
He was born here in the Jewish quarter.
- I live in the city in the Jerusalem,
an old city that I hear the church bells,
Arabs and I hear the Jews praying.
So, it would really bother me very much
if I wouldn't live here
and I wouldn't get used to it.
Because I got used to it,
it's like part of hearing the trees shaking.
It also makes me feel very safe here,
because I know
Saddam Hussain is bombing.
He would never bomb the old city of Jerusalem,
Because it's also his holiest place.
- [praying and worshipping]
- God said you should learn and do.
So, first you have to learn.
I start studying at seven-thirty and then we finished at seven-thirty everynight.
No one says that you have to do this,
while you are studying
But it says in the Gumorah,
the people of Israel, who keep the Torah
They're like a candle, that it always moves.
- .... when yo meet a Jew like me,
who is not religious,
do you feel like it's your personal job
to bring me closer to Judaism?
- Some people have to bring others closer,
some people have to bring their selves closer
And some people just have
to sit and learn.
Then, do what God tells them.
Each person has his own qualities.
Some people have quality to do this.
Each person does whatever she - whatever.
Each person really can't do this
with the reason to do something.
- And you, what's your reason?
- I still don't know.
- What do you think?
You have a--
- You have to...
- Instinct?
- I still don't know.
[chuckles]
- In 1948, Israelies fought what they
call the war of Indepence.
Palestinians call it the catastrophe.
As a result of the war, seven hundred
and fifty thousand Palestininans
fled or were forced off their land
and became refugees
Refugee camps were set up
in neighboring Arab states.
In 1967, Israel conquered
the Gaza Strip and the West Bank.
Many of the camps came under
Israeli military occupation.
The ... refugee come is home
to more than 11,000 Palestinians.
The refugees who fled Israel in 1948,
their children, grandchildren
and great grandchildren
still live here.
- My name is
Sanabel Hassan Abd'el Jawad.
My name means giving and loyalty
and, it's also the symbol of love.
We're from Zakarieh. The Jews kicked
us off our land and put us in this camp.
This camp used to be just tents.
In our family, we each have our own bed.
Other families have seven people sleeping
in one room on the on the floor.
Or maybe two or three people
sleep in the same bed.
Other families have it really bad.
- Sanabel's father is a Journalist
and a local leader of the popular front
for The Liberation of Palestine.
A political faction that vehemently
opposes the peace process.
For the last two years,
he's been held in an Israeli jail.
However, no formal charges
have ever been brought against him.
And, he has never stood trial.
- This is the Holy Dome of the Rock.
Some prisoners made it for my dad--
prisoners from Ashkelon jail,
but from a different cell,
from Hamas.
I'm happy when I get a letter from my dad.
And also...
- [...] How do you feel when
you get a letter?
I feel happy that my dad --
[crying]
[sniff]
- Do you write letters to your father?
- We write letters.
We wrote one on his birthday
but they didn't deliver it.
Because we sent it with a stack of photographs.
♪ birthday song ♪
[talking in Palestinian]
[clapping]
- The last time I was in ...
I was a journalist during the Intifada
or Palestinian uprising.
The Intifada was born in the refugee camps.
Its heroes were Palestinian youth.
Their weapon was the stone.
- The camps were still considered dangerous.
Israelies just don't come here.
- Cucumbers! Cucumbers!
- My name is
Faraj Adnan Hassan Husein.
It was during the Intifada
and there was a curfew.
My friend Bassam throw a stone
through an open window...
and a soldier shot Bassam.
Killed him.
I wanted to cut the soldier in half.
Shoot him or blow him up
to avenge Bassam's death.
- Of course I throw stones!
Everyone should! Stones were --
In the Intifada the stone nearly
liberated half of Palestine!
They have guns and nuclear stuff.
All we have is a stone...
to defend ourselves.
- [....] Following the 1967 war,
groups of nationalist Jews
established settlements here
on what was previously Arab land.
Land, the settlers believe to be the Biblical land
of Judeah and Samaria.
The Israeli government actively encourage
the settlement of the occupied territories.
And today, there were more than
one hundred and fifty thousand settlers
living in the West Bank.
Beit-El is one of the largest
and oldest settlements.
Like all of the settlements, Beit-El is under
the close protection of the Israeli military.
Eventhough, I grew up only 20 minutes
from here, I had never visited Beit-El
or any other settlement before.
God promised us the land of Israel.
The Arabs came and took it!
I am surrounded by Arabs.
We'll talk about it later.
In the book of Genesis it says,
"Rise and walk the land."
Who is God speaking to?
Abraham, our forefather.
If Abraham didn't exist, me and
him and him wouldn't exist.
Even you wouldn't exist.
Moishe, what will you be
when you grow up?
I'll try to be an army commander...
Then I'll try to become
the Commander in Chief.
If I succeed maybe I'll be the
first religious Commander in Chief.
I want Barak to make a coalition
with the settler's party.
That's the perfect combination,
but it will never work out.
My name is Mosihe Bar Am.
I live in Beit-El.
It's a settlement, a place where
people who fight with Arabs live.
We fight because this land is ours.
If I could make my own future,
all the Arabs would fly away.
The Jews would stay
and the Temple would be rebuilt.
This fence separates us
from that Arab village.
Beit-el is surrounded by Arabs.
If the Arabs break in,
there's nothing we can do.
We're surrounded. We can't escape.
But we have oru family army to protect us.
We have our firing range.
And if the soldiers aim poorly, it's okay
because they might shoot an Arab!
- I can't shake your hands!
$$ - Why?
- Because it's not modest.
Resting on Shabbat is
a "mitzva" (a commandment).
The girls light the candles
and they set the table.
- She sets the table...
And I play with my computer!
A special Shabbat cup.
We cover the bread so it doesn't
see that we drink the wine first.
It's forbidden to rip toilet paper
on Shabbat.
So, I am pre-ripping it.
On Shabbat it's forbidden
to touch money.
It's forbidden to brush hair in case,
there are knots to work through.
When I@m a mom and big,
I'll set the table.
I'll cook food and invite guests.
Then, I'll rest. Then, I'll light candles
and go to synagogue.
Then, we'll have Shabbat dinner,
we'll have a Torah lesson.
In the morning w'll go
back to synagogue.
Then, we'll eat a meal
and go for a walk.
Then, I'll take mykids to friends
and we'll play games.
Then, I'll rest with my husband.
Then, we'll eat another meal
and I'll walk with my girlfriends.
We'll take the kids to the
playground and sit on the bench.
And when the sun sets...
we'll come home
and have the third meal.
Then, my husband will go to pray...
then, we all do "Havdala"
and then, another prayer.
Moishe, help me with the chairs.
-[Moishe] answering in ..
SS - He's glued to his computer.
I did it!
[praying in ....]
- [...] checkpoints are situated at all crossings
between the West Bank and Israel.
West Bank Palestinians cannot leave
the West Bank, travel to Jerusalem
or even cross from one Palestinian area
to another with the ...permit
issued by the Israeli military.
Checkpoints are used to separate
the Israeli from the Arabs.
To search us and humiliate us.
I'm and Arab. If you're an Arab,
you're prohibited from enetering Israel.
They say, "you're am Arab
and will remain an Arab!"
to a Jew they say, "Welcome"
and to an American, "Welcome."
They can go whereever they want.
- [...] For Palestinians, checkpoints are
daily reminder of the occupation.
Most Israelis feel the checkpoints
make life in Israel safer.
That they offer some form of protection
from acts of terrorism.
As an Israeli travelling in a car
with Israeli license plates,
checkpoints are no inconvenience to me
because I'm usually waived right through.
- Welcome to Israel!
- The first time I cried was on May 9th
when I heard the war was over.
It was the first time I cried
since they killed my family.
- You only cried once?
- I just once.
When we left Poland, we decided
that if we're leaving our birthplace...
then, we should go somewhere safer.
Where the Holocaust could
never happen again.
So, we decided to come to Israel.
- Some Jews think that God
made this State.
But it's a fact - after war the Jews
came here and established the State.
So, it's not God.
- Do you believe in God?
- What?
I don't.
I don't believe God could
have watched...
and not do anything.
- So you don't believe?
Do you believe or not?
- Yes? Or No?
- You have to decide for yourself.
- But we're asking you!
- I believe it was the hand of fate
that kept me alive.
- So, you don't believe in God.
- It was the hand of fate.
So, there's room for God as well.
- Do you believe in a Higher Power?
[laughing]
[praying and worshipping]
[church bell ringing]
- [....] The Temple Mount or Harram Al Sharif
is holy to both Jews and Muslims.
For Jews, this is where the Jewish temples
stood 2000 years ago.
For Muslims, this is the side
Muhammad's ascension to heaven
and the home of two
of Islam's holiest shrines.
The Dome of the Rock and the Al Aqsa Mosque.
When I enter Al Aqsa,
I feel something deep in my heart.
It's so beautiful. I feel that
I am in the presence of God.
[praying in foreign language]
- [Beezee] Just below the Al Aqsa Mosque
is the Western Wall...
Judaism's holiest site.
- Look at you! Look at you!
- [laughing]
- Almost didn't recognize you.
- He has two hats.
He has one hat - special hat
we've got from chavis and a suit for chavis.
And during the week, he has a lesser expensive hat - but it's still beautiful.
And everyday, he has to wear
pants and a jacket.
It doesn't have to be matching or suit-like
but just something that gives the honor to the ...
[praying]
[ceremony in ...]
♪ singing in foreign language ♪
- [Beezee] The Western Wall is also
a major tourist destination.
Any Jew who visits Jerusalem comes here.
I arranged to meet the twins here
one morning,
but when they arrived,
they didn't wanna go anywhere near the wall.
Like many secular Israelis, the twins
want little to do with religious Jews.
♪ singing in Jew ♪
[trumpet]
- We don't know these people,
they have different opinions.
Like if we yell something
they didn't agree with.
They'd eat us alive!
That guy over there.
He's the scariest.
All these old guys scare me.
- Daniel isn't the only one who's
scared. I'm scared too!
I just don'w show it. Cause
he's a scaredy-cat and I'm not.
♪ singing in Jew? ♪
- [Beezee] I used to come here
a lot as a kid.
And following tradition, I put notes
in the wall for God to read.
I'd wished for a new bicycle or that some girl
in my class would fall in love with me.
But mostly, I wished for peace.
- I want to write a note too.
- [foreign language]
- I wish our shool wins
the volleyball championship.
I put a note in the wall
for Tuesday's game.
Maybe it'll helo.
[phone ringing]
[foreign language]
I was scared to death.
I'd rather visit an Arab village
than be here with...
all these religious people.
- [Beezee] Sanabel is a member of a group
that uses traditional dance
to tell the story of the refugees.
The dance celebrates the resilience
of the Palestinian people
and their dream of Palestinian statehood.
[clapping]
♪ My Homeland, my Homeland! ♪
♪ Our symbols are
the pen and the sword ♪
♪ not empty words and quarrels. ♪
♪ We are driven by our glory
and our duty to fulfill our pact. ♪
♪ Our pride ♪
♪ An honorable cause
and a fluttering flag. ♪
♪ Oh your joy in your eminance
victorious over your enemis ♪
[clapping]
♪ My Homeland, my Homeland!
[cheering and applauding]
- [Beezee] After months of practice,
Yarko and Daniel's volleyball team
made it to the Jerusalem Finals.
The team that wins this game will represent
Jerusalem in the National Championship.
[whistle blowing]
[cheering and applauding]
I'd go back to the Wall to write
a note asking that we win a game
But maybe not,
'cause I did that last time.
And we lost B. Z.!
[beep]
[foreign dialogue]
♪ singing ♪
- [B.Z.] A couple of months ago,
Faraj was spotted by a school coach
as a promising sprinter.
He's represented the Deheishe Refugee Camp
at the first ever Palestinian Track Meet.
And the camp is counting on Faraj
to place first in the 100 meter dash.
[chopper]
[drum roll]
- If I come in first
you bring me a present!
- I will. And if you lose?
-I'll kiss everyone's hand!
Deal!
[cheering Faraj]
[foreign dialogue]
-The winner of the 100 meter race
is Hatem Amri from Beit Jala.
In second palce
Faraj Adnan from Deheishe.
- B.Z.? You know that boy?
The runner?
[dog barking]
Did he win?
Did he win the finals?
- Did he cry? Sometimes we
also cry after a race.
[door opening]
[water flowing]
- [...] My beloved Sanabel, Vida, Bisen, ....
Here I am, writing to you once again.
Knowing that you are waiting for my release
with the utmost patient.
My arrest was extended for six more months.
I am waiting for your visit to see you
and always remember that my love
for you all is unlimited.
Over here! Everybody!
Move!
Folks, please move back!
Does anyone speak Hebrew and Arabic?
They don't understand me.
Ask them if anyone speaks Hebrew and Arabic.
Everyone back.
[foreign dialogue]
Does anyone speak
Hebrew and Arabic?
Folks! Is there someone
who can translate?
- [B.Z.] The journey to the jail
takes about four hours.
And the family usually spends a few more hours waiting to their allowed-in for thirty minute visit.
[foreign dialogue]
-[B.Z.] My requests to enter the jail
were denied.
The Israeli authorities views Sanabel's father as a security risk.
And he's allowed no visitors other than
his immediate family.
When an Arab sees me he thinks
I am one of those who took his land.
They think it their land
and we think it's ours.
We know it's ours.
It's not for Israel.
It's for the Arabs. It's ours.
This is my land!
I was born and raised here.
You have no right to take it!
- But I understand them because
they were thrown out of here,
fifty years ago.
They feel very... very small,
very like
`because they were thrown out that way.
I think this is our country
and it's also theirs.
When extremists say the other side
shouldn't live here, that's wrong.
There was a war
and we conquered it.
I don't know what to do now.
The Jewish people still occupy
our land - they haven't left any land.
If they want to, they could return
and occupy this camp.
They occupy people
and put them in prison.
This is wrong.
For me, there is no peace now.
I have proof that I own this land
and I have the right to build on it!
Then, there will be peace. We won't
harm the Jews and they won't harm us.
- I can't find it,
no problem.
"Cause God didn't give the land
of Israel to Abraham many times.
He only gave him the land once.
And because of that one time...
The land belongs to us.
It's not far.
Here, I found it!
And Abraham was 99 years old.
And God said to ABraham: I will
give to you and to your desccendants...
all the land of Canaan
for an everlasting possession.
And this blessing passed
from Abraham to Isaac to Jacob.
ANd an angel changed
Jacob's name to "Israel."
And why we are called "Israel?"
We're named after him!
These are our land deeds.
They're really old, grandmother.
- [Grandmother] answering in foreign language
Here's one from 1942.
- This one's from 1931.
- And this was the key to our house.
I took it with me.
- It's so old, grandmother.
- [B.Z.] The village that Faraj's grandmother
comes from is inside Israel.
Just beyond the check point.
Since, they don't have permits,
the only way to get in there
was to sneak pass the checkpoint
in a car with Israeli licensed plates.
- The Jews destroyed it, blew it up
so no one could say we had a country.
- Was our house right there?
- In the walley
- And the spring was back there.
All this is our land.
Could anyone taste this pure air
and then, go to Deheishe!?
God curse Deheishe
and the day it was built!
That was Abu Zakaria's house.
That iron beam was part of your
Grandfather Isa's house.
If you were united,
you would have defeated them.
United? There was a massacre
at Dir Yasin and they took the women.
Does anyone want to see
his daughter or wife stabbed?
his brother or daughter slaughtered?
- So you ran away?
- Yes!
- And took refuge in the camps.
- In Bethlehem and other places.
Here's an Israeli Star.
Should I kick it?
[grasping breath]
[foreign dialogue]
- This is our house!
- The house my grandfather built?
-That's right.
- Where was the front door?
- The door was by that
almond tree, over there.
May you, your father, son,
and grandson all return to live here.
With God's Will.
- With God's Will.
- And this key, don't ever neglect it.
Keep it with you always.
I want to pray here.
God is great.
Peace upon you.
- My right is to return to Ras Abu Ammar.
It's not just about checkpoints...
and freedom of movement.
I want to return to Ras Abu Ammar!
I believe that if not my generation,
then, perhaps the next
will liberate Palestine
and return to Ras ABu Ammar.
Refugees do not worry!
Wewill sacrifice our blood!
Negotiator, don't sell out!
From Deheishe to Baghdad!
One Indestructible Front!
There will be no peace
until colonialism ends!
We say his openly
We don't to see Zionists!
Children of the Stone!
This is not peace!
Let the flag fly high!
We don't want to see Israel!
People come and gather!
The Martyr has sacrificed his blood!
March people march!
- Whta's your name?
- Faraj Adnan.
Where do you live? Deheishe refugee camp.
Where are you from originally? Ras Abu Ammar.
My dream is to return to my land.
If I can't return, then I'll give the key to my children and grandchildren.
Just as my grandparents gave it to me.
This deer, does it like freedom or captivity?
Freedom!
Good. Do you like freedom?
Yes.
Do the children of Palestine live in freedom?
No.
Can someone draw a picture that shows how you feel?
Are you free like the deer? Or is something obstructing your freedom?
Like the people who are prevented from going to pray in Jerusalem.
This is a child holding a stone saying, "I will kill them."
Another child is crying "They killed my mother, father, and sister-"
"May God curse them."
These children are going to Jerusalem.
But the soldiers won't allow them across the checkpoint.
This is Jerusalem, the chiuldren and this is the barricade.
What does our religion say-
Who does Jerusalem belong to?
The Palestinians.
The Canaanites.
The Palestinian People!
The Moslems-
The Palestinians are pushing it! They want Jerusalem as their capital.
They can keep wanting!
Jerusalem is 10 minutes from Deheishe camp.
I've never been to Jerusalem.
I'd like to visit our capital and pray there.
See Jerusalem and the Dome of the Rock to see what's inside it.
Of course I haven't visited it because they don't let us in.
We have to really think about it and have the whole world discuss it.
The smartest people in the world should decide about Jerusalem.
I'd never return Jerusalem. God forbid-
I'd clear out the Arabs from the Mount of Olives and all Jerusalem.
Until the 1967 war, Jerusalem was a divided city.
West Jerusalem was Israeli and east Jerusalem, including the old city,
was in Jordanian hands. Jews did not have access to their holy sites.
When Israel conquered the West Bank, all of Jerusalem came under Israeli rule.
[Men praying/chanting]
Every year, Israelis from all over the country come to Jerusalem to celebrate
the city's reunification.
In recent years,the settlers' movement has organized a Jerusalem Day parade
that marches through the Muslim quarter on their way to the western wall.
[Men singing]
Masmud and his family are Jerusalem Arabs.
Unlike the kids who live in the refugee camp, Masmud doesn't need a permit
to cross the check point. And he can move freely around the city.
[Men singing]
[Men clapping/singing] The people of Israel are alive!
They say today is the celebration of the reunification of Jerusalem.
But Jerusalem isn't for the Jews. It's for Arabs. This is just a provocation.
The Jews act like they own this land.
How would you feel?
My heart wants to burst.
[People singing and clapping with music]
I support Hamas and Hezbollah.
They kill women and children but they do it for their country.
The more Jews we kill, the fewer there will be.
Until they're almost gone.
When we blow up buses, we anger them!
[Music playing]
Exactly on Wednesday. At about five o'clock-
He died. Murdered. On the spot.
My friend told me how it happened-
This is Ephraim's car and this is the terrorist's car.
The terrorists overtook them-
Then slowed down and started shooting.
[Heavy gunshots firing]
One bullet in the head and he was killed. Murdered actually.
And Ita, his mom died in the hospital.
It's hard to accept. I met him at the "mikva" (ritual bath) every week.
The last time we met I said "See you next week."
He said, "God Willing." I said, why "God Willing?"We meet every week!
That was the last week he was alive.
[Boy whispering a song while pedalling his bike]
Such a good friend.
I can't accept it. I just can't accept that Ephraim's dead.
"Ephraim Tzur, 12 years old"
"Murdered with his mother by terrorists"
Murdered.
And I have a proof.
On the grave it says, "God will avenge his blood."
They only write that for murder.
When you place a stone, it's like you're identifying with the grave.
Actually, Ephraim is doing OK in heaven.
They gave him nice things.
He'll be OK up there.
Still if I could have one wish, I'd ask God to send the Messiah-
Then all the dead will return-
Especially those murdered by terrorists.
When I see them being killed, I asked myself-
Why? It's so stupid. It could be prevented.
In war both sides suffer. Maybe there's a "winner" but what's a winner?
People on BOTH sides die.
Both sides lose.
I try to imagine what they (the soldiers) went through.
It's hard to imagine, 'cause if you weren't there, how could you know?
Just like the Holocaust- people say they know what it felt like.
Bullshit.
You can be sad. But you can't really know the pain they experienced.
Matan?
He's in room 9.
Hi!
What happened?
A missile hit and exploded a meter and a half away.
Did you think you would die?
Well, maybe...No. I don't think so.
Are you afraid it might happen again if you go back to the army?
There's no chance I'll be going back to the same unit.
Why? -Because my medical profile...
What was your profile?
97 points.
That's good right?
You know why it's only 97 points?
Circumcision.
Hahaha!
That's the missing 3 points?
So NOBODY gets 100!
So what do you think about going to the army?
-There's no rush. -It's an open question.
My problem is I don't want to shoot people.
I might want to be in a combat unit but I don't want to kill people.
And in a combat unit you have to kill people, right?
Tough question. I also don't want to kill people.
Sometimes you have no choice
because either you die or
your enemy dies.
[children talking and playing]
- [B.Z.] Military service is compulsory
in this reel.
But altar orthodox Jewish boys
like Shlomo are exempt.
Instead of serving in the army,
they continue their religious studies
while receiving a monthly stipend
from the government.
- The place where we study,
instead of going to the army,
is good as much as going to the army.
- People who go to the army
also have to study!
- If you're going to live here,
you have to protect the State!
- And I think by what we are learning,
we're doing enough to give something to the state.
- So go to the army and then, learn.
Doesn't everybody deserve to learn?
"Learn!"
- I think that the Torah has is equal as I think.
What I think I could do,
Torah could do too.
- One of them said on TV,
"I don't know how to use a gun."
We'll teach you how to use a gun!
- The Palestinian sometime look,...
I'm not saying that the Jews are very very innocent but they look for fights too sometimes
[laughing]
Kids, for example, I could be walking down the street and hear an Arab cursing me.
Sometimes, he could like curse back and then, he'll hurt you.
Some kids like will tear you apart
and beat you up until you're bleeding.
And some kids will just like hunt you,
finished punching you and go.
I never got into like being a friend to an Arab but like, I did get into like
saying hi in the streets or stuffs like that.
[foreign dialogue]
Sometimes, it's not too much fun.
- [B.Z.] Did you get into a fight?
- Yeah!
- [B.Z.] Have you met each other before?
- Nope!
- [B.Z] But you're neighbors?
......
- [B.Z.] Do you know any Jews who have
Palestinian friends?
- If you were like, I know a lot of fathers
like ... ....
nice communication between each other
but kids almost never.
[burp]
[giggling]
[laughing]
[burp]
[exchanging burps]
[foreign dialogue]
- I don't know any Arab kids
and I don't want to meet any.
- I don't like talking to Jews.
I know them!
They're mean and deceitful.
Since, the time of the Prophet Mohammed.
They betrayed him in battle
and fought against him.
- Beside if I met an Arab,
my friends would call me a wimp!
- When I see a Jew I want to grab a stone
and throw it at him.
or at his car.
I even think of killing him.
- Some Arab kids might become terrorists.
Think about this.
- Any Jew who sees me would think I'm a terrorist.
They think about their fathers and uncles
who have been killed.
So, we both think of the same thing.
We each think of our relatives
who have been killed by other side
So we each want to kill each other!
- This is Faraj.
[foreign dialogue]
- How old is he? He looks like
a runner. Is he taller than us?
- [B.Z.] He's small for his age.
- You can see he's a little crazy, but nice.
- Does he speak Hebrew?
- [B.Z.] No, but he speaks some English.
- Why don't we meet them?
- They don't want to.
They didn't invite us.
- You're so silly!
- [B.Z.] Would you talk politics with him?
- I'd rather talk sports, not politics!
- Enough! Be serious!
- [Dad] You can't always avoid things.
- I'm not avoiding anything.
There's more to life than sport!
- [B.Z.] Do you want to meet
Jewish children?
- I'm willing!
- I don't want them to come here.
- Even if he understands me,
when he grows up he'll
take his father's side against me,
otherwise, his father would kill him.
He'd rather displaced us
than join us and be displaced.
- You're dogmatic. You have to understand
their thinking then, respond.
- Of course I'm dogmatic! What do you
expect after all we've been through?
- Maybe, he'll understand you. When he grows up he might come to help you.
- Maybe he'll be displaced
just like you.
- He could never handle one-tenth
of what we went through!
They killed your brother
and you want to make friends
with their sons?
- But they didn't kill Bassam.
- Their father might have.
- I believe all children are innocent.
- Do I want to meet Jewish children?
No?
- But I'm a Jewih boy.
- You are an American Jewish boy.
Do you speak Hebrew?
Speak Hebrew!
-[speaking in Hebrew]
- That's all?
- No, I speak perfect Hebrew.
Because, I studied here.
Here in Jerusalem, Israel, Palestine,
- I'm half Israeli.
- You're also half American
not just Israeli.
It's not a problem.
I was talking about authentic Jews.
Not Americans.
Not mixed.
- Okay! My brother is an authentic Jew
and I'm an authentic Jew too!
- He's an authentic Jew?
- I'm sure we'll never return to our villages.
I'm absolutely positive.
We will never have our homeland.
I just want on thing; remove the borders.
Take away the checkpoints.
We want to live with them!
- If we refuse to meet Jewish kids,
and they refuse to meet us...
there will never be peace
between us and the Jews.
Nor between two countries.
We Arabs are killing each other
because of them.
And you want me to become friends
with them?
- Israelis will never understand us.
Neither adults nor kids!
- Why is it the children's fault?
- The children will grow up!
They might feel with us!
- They won't feel.
- No Palestinan child ever tried to explain
our situaton to the Jews.
Arabs and Jews should meet.
But Netanyahu...
not politicians.
I want children to meet.
- I have a question.
Those twins...
Do they want to come here?
- Faraj, I want to meet you
and to listen to your opinion
because I want to know what's your opinion...
- [B.Z.] Even if...
- even if we don't have the same...
opinion.
- A telephone number?
- Yeah!
- I have a telephone number.
- I talk with you now..(check again)
- Hello. Who's that?
- B.Z.?
Yes. What's up?
- We just interviewed Faraj
- [Yarko] What did he say?
- [Yarko] Hello?
- Hello!
- [Yarko] Faraj?
- Hi
- How'd you do?
- What do you say?
- I think...
- That we have to think about it.
- No, I thought about it.
If you want to go then...
I feel I should be there.
- I don't want you to come.
It's not up to you Yarko.
- It is too.
- Right mom? It's not up to him.
- We're in the picture, too.
- I didn't say you weren't in the picture.
I said you weren't coming.
- Look, I trust B.Z. and the crew
and the people who invited you.
But the final responsibility is ours.
- Somthing could happen.
- So?
- There could be a curfew.
I'd feel safer if you were going to Paris.
It's the territories and the army.
This is not a walk to the grocery store.
What do you think?
- They need it to be their day
and I respect that.
- We have our own needs.
- Our needs are our fears.
Let's face it!
Is the Hamas there?
- There are Hamas-niks everywhere
- Will it be dangerous?
- No. If it was dangerous,
I wouldn't let you go.
And you're guests, don't forget.
This is a checkpoint.
- Mom, we know what a checkpoint is.
- Look, Arabs waiting to be searched.
- It's not fair! It's their land.
Why do they have to be searched?
- It's their land but we don't want
to blow up. It's complicated.
- Look, a cop, a cop,
a Palestinian cop!
So mom, it's real close huh?
- 15 minutes.
[convesation in ...]
- Hi!
- Daniel?
- Yarko!
- Welcome to Deheishe Camp.
- You're running with this?
- No, ...
- No, but the shoes....
- Yeah!
- Yes?
During the Intifada, this was the center
of the clashes.
These are bullet holes.
Many people were martyred here.
Boys threw stones and the soldiers
would shoot at them.
- and he's dead here?
- Real bulets or rubber bullets?
- Real ones.
- Real ones?
- Look, don't speak Israeli (Hebrew)
here in the camp Deheishe.
Because the Arabs don't like anything.
- Don't like Israeli people?
- Yeah!
- Here?
"Victory is ours"
The land's thirst will be quenched
with blood. - Hamas
- I'm Daniel.
- Here, here.
- Hello!
- Welcome!
♪ singing while playing ♪
- Okay, the translators are here.
- How do you feel after our day together?
- I used to think that anyone
who liked the Hamas was totally insane.
Some of the kids here like the Hamas
and now I can understand why.
The graffiti might make me uncomfortable
but I can understand it.
If I were them,
I'd feel the same way.
- [Faraj] I feel torn inside.
$ Part of me wants to connect with you
and part doesn't.
- Just like all Palestinians
aren't Hamas-niks.
Not all Israelis kill Arabs.
- [B.Z.] Motassim, why are you crying?
- I remember how they killed my brother.
He went to herd the sheep...
Let Ahmed tell the story.
- He went to herd the sheep on the mountain
with his friends.
They saw people throwing stones
and went to join them.
A soldier stood on a jeep
and shot him with one bullet.
- They shot him?
- With just one bullet, Bassam was gone
and everything was gone.
For the first time,
I felt that this other nation here...
who hate us and don't want us here.
- Both sides have to deal with it.
- Israelis are also killed.
We've also lost people.
- It's not one-sided.
On TV we see pictures of people killed by the Hamas.
- What prevents us from knowing
one another is the checkpoints.
The Jews prevent us so we can't visit
each other whenever we want.
- [B.Z.] Faraj, what's up?
- This afternoon, I started thinking
that B.Z. will leave soon.
And now we've become friends
with Daniel and Yarko.
And they will forget our friendship
as soon as B.Z. leaves.
And all our effort will be in vain.
I feel the world has changed
for the worse.
There's no peace.
There are wars and catastrophes.
One can't begin to imagine his future
or solve his problems.
One's plan for the future
may never happen.
Because the life we live doesn't allow us
to accomplish our dreams.
- It wans't easy to meet,
with all the checkpoints and stuff.
Faraj called us a lot.
Mostly, we didn't return his calls.
Well, at the beginning we did.
He didn't understand.
He thought it was so simple to meet.
He said, "I'll come to you,
I'll cross the checkpoint."
But it was more complicated.
- I would like to meet
more Jewish people and children.
Because many of them are innocent.
Even some of the adults.
They didn't all encourage the occupation
of our land.
I'd like to meet them because
if we increase our interactions,
our respect for one another
will grow.
- There is no chance of peace without
meetings between Jews and Arabs.
But I am not the one
who will meet Arabs
and do those things.
That needs to be done
by people who are...
in their thirties or older.
Ministers and Members of Parliament.
They need to meet Arabs and to start to do
something about the issue.
- Peace between you and me is impossible
unless we get to know each other.
Our fathers are at war and if I don't know you, I can't have peace with you.
Also, you must return what you have taken away from me.
The land must be returned. You can stay here, but as a guest.
I wouldn't really have any interest in that. In like meeting Arab kids
and speaking to them about all kind of stuff but I would like to be nice, you know,
that no fights and all kinds of stuff would be happening around.
Not really like close friendship but at least like kind of a small "peace process."
I'm more concerned with my own problems.
In the movie, you asked me to respond to questions as an Israeli.
But I have my own concerns. Like friends and volleyball, and-
I want there to be peace here. I really do.
I just don't deal with it day to day.
[Wind blowing, car passing, horse cart passing]]
[Piano playing, baby crying]
[Voice singing]